Finding Aid for the John Phillip Hyatt Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
John Phillip Hyatt Papers
c. 1927-1972
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0220
23.51 linear_feet
Biographical Sketch
Born to Robert Lee and Mamie (Stanley) Hyatt on Feb. 16, 1909 in Monticello, Arkansas, J. Philip Hyatt married Elizabeth Bard of Brooklyn, Connecticut in 1932. The Hyatts had three sons—James Lee, Charles Sidney, and David Philip.
Hyatt was educated at Baylor University (A.B., 1929), Brown University (A.M., 1930), and Yale University (B.D., 1933, Ph.D., 1938). His doctoral work was in the field of Ancient Near Eastern Studies. In addition, he studied at the American School of Oriental Research in Jerusalem (1931-32) and the University of Marburg in Germany (1932). He received honorary degrees from Christian Theological Seminary (D.D., 1967), Baylor University (L.L.D., 1969), and Texas Christian University (D.H.L., 1969).
Hyatt was ordained a Baptist minister in 1929 and he served as minister of the Hull Memorial Baptist Church in Cheshire, Connecticut (1932-35). In 1946 he transferred his ministerial credentials to the Christian Church, Disciples of Christ and he was active in various Disciples efforts including the Disciples Historical Society, the Disciples Divinity House of Vanderbilt Divinity School, the Panel of Scholars to Re-examine Disciples’ Thought and Doctrine, as well as in his own local congregation, Woodmont Christian Church in Nashville, Tennessee.
Hyatt taught at Wellesley College (1935-41) before moving to Vanderbilt University where he became full professor of Old Testament in 1944 and where he served until his death in 1972. In addition, Hyatt served as visiting professor or fellow at the University of Chicago (1944), Garret Biblical Institute (1945), Union Theological Seminary in New York (1950), Iliff School of Theology (1958), Perkins School of Theology (1961) and Hebrew Union College (1952).
Also active in academic administration, Hyatt was an important figure at Vanderbilt Divinity School where he served as Acting Dean (1956-57). He also served on and often chaired the influential Personnel and Policy Committee of the Divinity School. In addition, he chaired the Graduate Department of Religion (1944-64) and served as the Divinity School representative to the University Senate. Hyatt’s role in the controversy over the expulsion of black civil right rights activist and Divinity School student James Lawson in 1961 deserves mention. While most of the Divinity School faculty chose to resign in protest of the University action in expelling Lawson, Hyatt was one of the few who did not but rather fight from within the university to change policiesd.
A prolific author, Hyatt wrote or edited nine books as well as numerous scholarly articles. In addition, he wrote a wide variety of devotional and educational materials such as Sunday school lesson, etc.
From 1945 until his death, Hyatt served as a member of the Old Testament section of the Standard Bible Committee, the committee sponsored by the National Council of Churches which undertook the translation and production of the Revised Standard Version of the Bible. As a member of the Committee, Hyatt also engaged in public defense of the new translation against fundamentalist attacks. Other ecumenical activities include his serving on the Faith and Order Commission of the World Council of Churches.
Active in professional societies, Hyatt’s memberships included the Society of Religion in Higher Education, the American Oriental Society, the American Academy of Religion, the British Society of Old Testament Study, and the Society of Biblical Literature, of which he was elected President for 1956.
J. Philip Hyatt suffered a heart attack at his office desk at Vanderbilt Divinity School and died on Nov. 6. 1972.
1909 Born on February 16 in Monticello, Arkansas to Robert Lee and Mamie (Stanley) Hyatt.
1925-29 Student at Baylor University, Waco, Texas. Majored in English Literature and Greek with a minor in History. Graduated A.B. (summa cum laude) in 1929.
1929 Ordained to the ministry in the Southern Baptist Church.
1929-30 Student at Brown University. Major in Biblical Literature with minor in Philosophy. Graduated A.M. in 1930.
1930-33 Student at Yale Divinity School. Graduated B.D. (magna cum laude) in 1933.
1931-32 Student at American School of Oriental Research in Jerusalem for seven months and student at University of Marburg in Germany for two months. Traveled extensively in Middle East and Europe.
1932 Married Elizabeth Bard of Brooklyn, Connecticut. The Hyatts had three sons—James Lee, Charles Sidney, David Philip.
1933-35 Pastor of Hull Baptist Church, Cheshire, Connecticut.
1935-41 Instructor (1935-38) and Assistant Professor (1938-41) of Biblical History at Wellesley College.
1938 Graduated with Ph.D. in Ancient Near Eastern Studies from Yale University.
1941 Author, The Treatment of Final Vowels in Early Neo-Babylonia. New Haven: Yale University Press, 1941.
1941-44 Associate Professor of Old Testament at Vanderbilt University.
1944-72 Professor of Old Testament at Vanderbilt University.
1944-64 Chair, Graduate Department of Religion of Vanderbilt University. Hyatt had a leading role in the development of the Ph.D. program in Religion at Vanderbilt.
1944 Visiting Professor, University of Chicago (Winter).
1945 Visiting Professor, Garrett Biblical Institute (Summer).
1945-72 Member, Old Testament Section of the Standard Bible Committee, sponsored by the National Council of Churches, which produced the Revised Standard Version of the Bible. Hyatt also engaged in public defense of the new version against fundamentalist attacks.
1946 Transferred ministerial credentials to the Christian Church, Disciples of Christ. Hyatt was active in various Disciples organizations and activities.
1947 Author, Prophetic Religion. Nashville: Abingdon, 1947.
1948-49 Editor, Journal of Biblical Literature.
1949-50 President, Southern Section, Society of Biblical Literature.
1950 Visiting Professor, Union Theological Seminary in New York (Summer).
1951 Editor, Vanderbilt Studies in the Humanities, I. Nashville: Vanderbilt University Press, 1951.
1952 Ford Faculty Fellow, Hebrew Union College, Cincinnati.
1954-61 Member, North American Section, Commission on Worship of the Commission on Faith and Order, World Council of Churches.
1956 Author, The Book of Jeremiah: Introduction and Exegesis in The Interpreters Bible V. New York: Abingdon Press, 1956.
1956-57 Acting Dean, Vanderbilt Divinity School. An important figure in the history of the Divinity School, Hyatt also served on the influential Personnel and Policy Committee and chaired the Biblical Department of the school.
1956-57 President, Society of Biblical Literature. During his tenure as president, Hyatt and the Society were embroiled in a controversy with the Aramaic Bible Society over the age and value of the so-called “Yonan Codex.” Hyatt was also a member of the American Oriental Society, the American Academy of Religion, the British Society of Old Testament Study, and the Society for Religion in Higher Education.
1957-63 Member, Panel of Scholars to Re-examine the Disciples Thought and Doctrine.
1958 Author, Jeremiah: Prophet of Courage and Hope. Nashville: Abingdon Press, 1958.
1958 Visiting Professor, Illif School of Theology (Summer).
1960-72 Member, Vanderbilt University Senate as representative of the Divinity School.
1961 Visiting Professor, Perkins School of Theology (Summer).
1961 Lawson Case. When the Vanderbilt University administration expelled black civil rights activist and Divinity School student James Lawson, most of the Divinity School faculty chose to submit resignations in protest. Hyatt was one of the few who did not.
1963 Death of son, James Lee Hyatt, at age 26.
1963 Author, The Prophetic Criticism of Israelite Worship (Goldenson Lecture for 1963). Cincinatti: Hebrew Union College Press, 1963.
1964 Author, The Heritage of Biblical Faith: An Aid to Reading the Bible. St. Louis: Bethany Press, 1964.
1965 Editor, The Bible in Modern Scholarship: Papers Read at the 100th Meeting of the Society of Biblical Literature. Nashville: Abingdon Press, 1965.
1965 Read paper at the Geneva Congress of the International Organization for Old Testament Study.
1967 Honorary D.D., Christian Theological Seminary, Indianapolis, Indiana.
1969 Honorary L.L.D., Baylor University.
1969 Honorary D.H.L., Texas Christian University.
1971 Author, Exodus (New Century Bible Commentary). London: Oliphants, 1971.
1972 Death by heart attack on Nov. 6, 1972.
Scope and Content Note
The J. Philip Hyatt papers comprise material dating from Hyatt’s student days to his death in 1972.
Correspondence files contain letters from 1936 to 1972 and are not at all complete with certain years much more fully represented than others. Important correspondents include W.F.
Albright, Nelson Glueck, George E. Mendenhall, Bruce Metzger, H.H. Rowley, Samuel Sandmel, Claus Westerman, and G. Ernest Wright.
Manuscript or print copies of most of Hyatt’s published writing output are present in the collection including manuscripts, scholarly and popular articles and book reviews, and devotional literature. Also included are his papers written while he was a student, a large collection of sermon and Sunday school notes, and texts of various speeches and addresses.
Material related to Hyatt’s Bible translation work as a member of the Standard Bible Committee from 1945 to 1972 are present including material related to the actual translation process of the Committee.
Hyatt’s teaching career is documented by a significant body of classroom related material including lecture notes, syllabi, papers written by students, etc.
Academic administration involvement is reflected in an extensive collection of Vanderbilt Divinity School and Vanderbilt University related materials. Divinity School materials included Personnel and Policy Committee items, Curriculum Committee items, material related to the Dean searches of 1956 and 1965-66 and to the Lawson case of 1961. A variety of Graduate Department of Religion (of which Hyatt was the chair from 1944-64) materials are present as well.
Hyatt’s involvement with the Vanderbilt University administration is reflected in papers relating to the University Research Council, the University Senate (of which Hyatt was the Divinity School representative), the Academic Policy Committee of the University Senate, and the Chancellor Search Committee which recommended Alexander Heard in 1965.
Hyatt was an active member in a variety of professional organizations. Present in the collection are quite a number of papers from his varied activities in the Society of Biblical Literature including files related to the Yonan Codex controversy of 1955-56 during which Hyatt, then president of the Society, was sued by the Aramaic Bible Society. Other organizations include the National Council on Religion in Higher Education, the Society for Old Testament Study, the American Association of Theological Schools, and the American School of Oriental Research.
Hyatt served as the alumni secretary for the Yale Divinity School class of 1933 and the collection includes extensive correspondence and other materials related to this activity.
An active churchman, Hyatt was deeply involved in various organizations and activities of his denomination, the Christian Church, Disciples of Christ. The collection included files from his work with the Disciples Divinity House of Vanderbilt Divinity School, the Disciples Historical Society, and the Disciples Panel of Scholars. Material relating to Hyatt’s ecumenical activities with the Faith and Order Commission of the World Council of Churches are also present.
A limited selection of papers related to Hyatt’s social justice activities can be found in these papers. An extensive selection of subject files relating primarily to Hyatt’s scholarly fields of Ancient Near Eastern and Old Testament studies are held in the collection. The presence of a variety of other subject files ranging from the American Indian religion to contemporary theology to Marxism reflects Hyatt’s wide range of interests.
Personal materials held include files on awards and honorary degrees, legal papers, files on family members, and appointment books covering the years 1951-72. Also present is a sizeable collection of short story fiction and other prose by Hyatt’s brother Robert L. Hyatt.
Acronyms:
AATS
American Association of Theological Schools
ANE
Ancient Near Eastern
ASOR
American School of Oriental Research
HUC
Hebrew Union College
NCRHE
National Council on Religion in Higher Education
ROTC
Reserve Officers Training Corps
RSV
Revised Standard Version
SBL
Society of Biblical Literature
- Series Description
  - Outgoing Correspondence (Box 1-2)
  - Incoming Correspondence (Box 1-2)
  - Writings (Box 3-11)
  - Publishing Activities (Box 12-13)
  - Bible Translation Activities (Box 14-15)
  - Academic Career (Box 16-24)
  - Organizations (Box 25-29)
  - Events (Box 29)
  - Church Activities (Box 30-32)
  - Community Activities
  - Subject Files (Box 33-41)
  - Personal (Box 41-42)
  - Writings by Others (Box 42)
- Correspondence
  - Outgoing, Feb. 1, 1936 - Nov. 8, 1972, Undated (Box 1)
  - Incoming, Abosi - Friess (Box 1)
  - Incoming. Galang - Zimmerman, Unidentified (Box 2)
- Writings and Speeches by Hyatt
  - Articles
    - Abraham,the Friend of God (Box 3, File 1)
    - "Adam" in Palestine (Box 3, File 1)
    - Ahasuerus (Box 3, File 1)
    - Amalekites (Box 3, File 1)
    - Ammonites (Box 3, File 1)
    - Amos (Box 3, File 1)
    - Answering Criticism of the Revised Standard Version (Box 3, File 2)
    - Archaeology and the Bible (Box 3, File 2)
    - Archaeology and the Translation of the Old Testament (Box 3, File 2)
    - Are the Criticisms Justified? (Box 3, File 2)
    - Are the Prophets Relevant Today? (Box 3, File 2)
    - Art (Box 3, File 2)
    - Arts and Crafts (Box 3, File 2)
    - Baal (Box 3, File 3)
    - Babylonia (Box 3, File 3)
    - Balaam (Box 3, File 3)
    - A Baylor Exile in New England (Box 3, File 3)
    - The Beginning of Jeremiah's Prophecy The Beginnings of the Hebrew Nation (Box 3, File 3)
    - Bethel (Deity) (Box 3, File 3)
    - The Bible in a Living Language (Box 3, File 3)
    - Biblical Archaeology in the College (Box 3, File 4)
    - A Bibliography of Important Books and Articles on Biblical Archaeology (Box 3, File 4)
    - A Bibliography of Millar Burrows' Works (Box 3, File 4)
    - The Birth of a Nation (Box 3, File 4)
    - The Book of Amos (Box 3, File 4)
    - The Book of Jeremiah and the Deuteronomists (Box 3, File 5)
    - Caleb (Box 3, File 6)
    - Chronicles, I and II (Box 3, File 6)
    - Circumcision (Box 3, File 6)
    - Cole Lectureship (Box 3, File 6)
    - The Compiling of Israel's Story (Box 3, File 6)
    - The Contribution of Archaeology to the Understanding of the Bible (Box 3, File 7)
    - The Contribution of the Hebrew Prophets (Box 3, File 7)
    - Crumbling Walls (Box 3, File 7)
    - "D" (Box 3, File 7)
    - The Date and Background of Zephaniah (Box 3, File 7)
    - The Dead Sea Discoveries (Box 3, File 7)
    - The Dead Sea Discoveries: Retrospect and Challenge (Box 3, File 7)
    - The Deity of Bethel and the Old Testament (Box 3, File 8)
    - The Deuteronomic Edition of Jeremiah (Box 3, File 8)
    - Deuteronomy (Box 3, File 8)
    - Deuteronomy (Box 3, File 8)
    - Discovery of the Oldest Biblical Manuscript (Box 3, File 8)
    - Dress (Box 3, File 8)
    - "E" (Box 3, File 9)
    - Eleazar (Box 3, File 9)
    - Esther (Box 3, File 9)
    - Esther (Box 3, File 9)
    - Exodus (Box 3, File 9)
    - Explaining the Text (July 1955) (Box 3, File 9)
    - Explaining the Text (August 1955) (Box 3, File 9)
    - Explaining the Text (September 1955) (Box 3, File 9)
    - Exploring the Bible Text (1960) (Box 3, File 10)
    - Exploring the Bible Text (1965) (Box 3, File 10)
    - Ezra (Box 3, File 10)
    - The Face of Temptation (Box 3, File 11)
    - Foreword, The Bible in Modern Scholarship (Box 3, File 11)
    - Freedom From Fear (Box 3, File 11)
    - Freud on Moses and the Genesis of Monotheism (Box 3, File 11)
    - From Hebrew to English (Box 3, File 11)
    - A Further Note on Boteah in Jer. 12:5 (Box 3, File 11)
    - Gaining Wisdom From Ancient Writings (Box 3, File 11)
    - Genesis (Box 3, File 11)
    - Gesenius, Friedrich Heinrich Wilhelm (Box 3, File 11)
    - Gilgamesh Epic (Box 3, File 11)
    - God in History (Box 3, File 11)
    - The God of Love in the Old Testament (Box 3, File 12)
    - The God Who Is Above All (Box 3, File 12)
    - Habakkuk (Box 3, File 13)
    - Haman (Box 3, File 13)
    - The Hebrew Shepherd Boy Who Became Prime Minister of Egypt (Box 3, File 14)
    - Helps for Teaching Studies in Christian Living (Box 3, File 14)
    - Hezekiah (Box 3, File 14)
    - Hoshea (Box 3, File 14)
    - How to Interpret the Prophets (Box 3, File 14)
    - Hunting (Box 3, File 14)
    - Iconic Representations of the Deified Sanctuary (Box 3, File 15)
    - The Impatience of Job (Box 3, File 15)
    - "J" (Box 3, File 15)
    - Jeremiah (Encyclopedia Americana) (Box 3, File 15)
    - Jeremiah (Encyclopedia Britannica) (Box 3, File 15)
    - Jeremiah (Box 3, File 15)
    - Jeremiah (Annotated Bible) (Box 3, File 16-17)
    - Jeremiah and Deuteronomy (Box 3, File 18)
    - Jeremiah and War (Box 3, File 18)
    - Jeremiah, Book of (Encyclopedia Americana) (Box 3, File 18)
    - Jeremiah, Book of (Encyclopedia Britannica) (Box 3, File 18)
  - Articles
    - Jeremiah 2-6 and Its Parallels (Box 4, File 1)
    - Jeremiah's Message for Today (August 1961) (Box 4, File 1)
    - Jeremiah's Message for Today (September 1961) (Box 4, File 1)
    - Joshua (Box 4, File 1)
    - Judges (Box 4, File 1)
    - Kings, I and II (Box 4, File 1)
    - Lessons From the Exile (Box 4, File 2)
    - Leviticus (Box 4, File 2)
    - Light from the Dead Sea (Box 4, File 2)
    - A Look at Twelve Books (Box 4, File 2)
    - Magic, Divination, and Sorcery (Box 4, File 2)
    - The Meaning of Suffering (Box 4, File 3)
    - The Meaning of the Scrolls (Box 4, File 3)
    - Meeting God Through Isaiah (Box 4, File 3)
    - The Message of the Seventh-Century Prophets for Today (Box 4, File 3)
    - The Messiah in Apocrypha and Pseudepigrapha (Box 4, File 3)
    - The Ministry of Scholarship (Box 4, File 3)
    - Moloch or Molech (Box 4, File 3)
    - Mordecai (Box 4, File 3)
    - Moses and the Ethical Decalogue (Box 4, File 3)
    - Nahum (Hastings Dictionary) (Box 4, File 4)
    - Nahum (Peake's Commentary) (Box 4, File 4)
    - A Nation's Decline and Downfall (Box 4, File 4)
    - Nehemiah (Box 4, File 4)
    - A Neo-Babylonian Parallel to Bethel-Sar-Eser, Zech. 7:2 (Box 4, File 4)
    - New Light on Nebuchadrezzer and Judean History (Box 4, File 4)
    - A New Look at the Dead Sea Scrolls (Box 4, File 4)
    - A Note on Yiwwada in Ps. 74:5 (Box 4, File 4)
    - Numbers (Box 4, File 4)
    - Obadiah (Annotated Bible) (Box 4, File 5)
    - The Old Testament Idea of God and Its Modern Relevance (Box 4, File 6)
    - The Old Testament View of Man (Box 4, File 6)
    - Old Testament Teaching About God's Discipline (Box 4, File 6)
    - On the Meaning and Origin of Micah 6:8 (Box 4, File 6)
    - The Origin and Meaning of Christian Baptism (Box 4, File 6)
    - The Origin of Mosaic Yahwism (Box 4, File 6)
    - The Original Text of Jeremiah 11:15-16 (Box 4, File 6)
    - The Peril From the North in Jeremiah (Box 4, File 7)
    - The Place of the Old Testament in the Christian Faith (Box 4, File 7)
    - Pre-Adamite (Box 4, File 7)
    - A Prophet Speaks to Our Day (Box 4, File 8)
    - Prophets of the Southern Kingdom (Box 4, File 8)
    - The Ras Shamra Discoveries and the Interpretation of the Old Testament (Box 4, File 9)
    - Reading the Bible Today (Box 4, File 9)
    - Religion in the Old Testament (Highroad, April 1948) (Box 4, File 9)
    - Religion in the Old Testament (Highroad. May 1948) (Box 4, File 9)
    - Religion in the Old Testament (Highroad, June 1948) (Box 4, File 9)
    - Religion in the Old Testament (Workers with Youth, April, 1948) (Box 4, File 9)
    - Religion in the Old Testament (Workers with Youth, May 1948) (Box 4, File 9)
    - Religion in the Old Testament (Workers with Youth, June 1948) (Box 4, File 9)
    - The Religion of the Old Testament (Box 4, File 10)
    - Responsible Under God (Box 4, File 10)
    - Resources for Use with Studies in Christian Living (Box 4, File 10)
    - The Revised Standard Version of the Bible (Box 4, File 10)
    - The Revised Standard Version (Box 4, File 10)
    - The Rise and Fall of a Nation (January 1949) (Box 4, File 11)
    - The Rise and Fall of a Nation (February 1949) (Box 4, File 11)
    - The Rise and Fall of a Nation (March 1949) (Box 4, File 11)
    - Road Map for the Book of Job (Box 4, File 11)
    - Ruth (Encyclopedia of Religion) (Box 4, File 11)
    - Ruth (Hastings Dictionary of the Bible) (Box 4, File 11)
    - "S" (Encyclopedia of Religion) (Box 4, File 12)
    - Samuel, I and II (Box 4, File 12)
    - Slave, Slavery (Box 4, File 12)
    - Smith, William Robertson (Box 4, File 12)
    - Solomon in All His Glory (Box 4, File 12)
    - The Sources of the Suffering Servant Idea (Box 4, File 12)
    - The Story of the English Bible (Aug. 13) (Box 4, File 13)
    - The Story of the English Bible (Aug. 22) (Box 4, File 13)
    - The Story of the English Bible (Aug. 29) (Box 4, File 13)
    - The Story of the English Bible (Sept. 5) (Box 4, File 14)
    - The Story of the English Bible (Sept. 12) (Box 4, File 14)
    - The Story of the English Bible (Sept. 19) (Box 4, File 14)
    - The Story of the English Bible (Sept. 26) (Box 4, File 14)
    - Support Bill S. 1161 (Box 4, File 14)
    - Textual Criticism of the Old Testament (Box 4, File 15)
    - This Bible Is for You (Box 4, File 15)
    - Torah in the Book of Jeremiah (Box 4, File 16)
    - The Translation and Meaning of Amos 5:23-24 (Box 4, File 16)
    - Tribal God (Box 4, File 16)
    - Understanding the Psalms in the Revised Standard (Box 4, File 17)
    - Version Values In Reading Job (Box 4, File 17)
    - The View of Man in the Qumran "Hodayot" (Box 4, File 17)
    - Was There an Ancient Historical Credo in Israel and an Independent Sinai Tradition? (Box 4, File 18)
    - Was Yahweh Originally a Creator Deity? (Box 4, File 19)
  - Articles, Books
    - What Are the Dead Sea Scrolls? (Box 5, File 1)
    - The Writing of an Old Testament Book (Box 5, File 1)
    - Why Do the Innocent Suffer (Box 5, File 1)
    - Yahweh as "The God of My Father" (Box 5, File 2)
    - Yehezkel Kaufmann's View of the Religion of Israel (Box 5, File 2)
    - Zephaniah (Box 5, File 2)
    - Untitled Sunday School Lesson (Box 5, File 2)
    - Miscellaneous Revisions for Articles (Box 5, File 3)
    - The Bible in Modern Scholarship (Draft) (Box 5, File 4)
  - Books
    - Exodus (Partial Draft) (Box 6, File 1)
    - Exodus (Complete Draft) (Box 6, File 2)
  - Books
    - A History of the Religion of Early Israel (Draft 1) (Box 7, File 1)
    - A History of the Religion of Early Israel (Draft 2) (Box 7, File 2)
    - A History of the Religion of Early Israel (Draft 3) (Box 7, File 3)
  - Books
    - The Heritage of Biblical Faith (Draft) (Box 8, File 1)
    - The Heritage of Biblical Faith (Proof) (Box 8, File 2)
    - Jeremiah: Prophet of Courage and. Hope (Box 8, File 3)
    - The Prophetic Criticism of Israelite Worship (Box 8, File 4)
    - The Treatment of Final Vowels in Early Neo-Babylonian (Box 8, File 5)
  - Book Reviews, Dissertation Bibliographies, Student Papers, Personal
    - Book Reviews: A - B (Box 9, File 1)
    - Book Reviews: C - G (Box 9, File 2)
    - Book Reviews: H - K (Box 9, File 3)
    - Book Reviews: L - N (Box 9, File 4)